<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-12-08T21:04:12+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Derisis13’s temporary blog</title><subtitle>Just some nerd rambling</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Server Setup Part 0 - Status Quo</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/12/08/statusquo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Server Setup Part 0 - Status Quo" /><published>2023-12-08T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/12/08/statusquo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/12/08/statusquo.html">&lt;p&gt;Since August I’ve been upgrading my home server setup.
It’s not yet 100% complete, but most of the architectural decisions are already behind me.
I wish to document this process so that others can learn from it and as a reminder for myself if I ever forget how I did something.
This is part zero of my writeup, which’ll be about the hardware and software used prior to the upgrade.
This should serve as a comparison baseline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nas&quot;&gt;NAS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a 2-bay Synology NAS for some years now.
It has been passed down to me from a family member along with drives to populate it.
It’s configured in RAID-1 with 2x 3TB HDDs.
This capacity was almost filled up, which meant it was time to migrate from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This NAS ran an SMB server, an ISCSI target, a VPN server, a DDNS updater, streamed music and had a BitTorrent client.
The processor and RAM limitations crippled the responsiveness of these services, and the configuration was very limited as well.
It was a good computer, but it no longer satisfied my needs - at least not for the price I wanted to pay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;linux-server&quot;&gt;Linux server&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To expand into additional services that my NAS couldn’t provide, I got a cheap laptop with a broken hinge (from a family member as well) and installed the XFCE spin of Fedora workstation on it.
I like this device for how simple it is: 5W idle power draw, 4-core Intel CPU (passively cooled by a piece of metal), the entire board being just one card, except the socketed RAM and the WLAN card (which I found has no black/whitelist).
Its IO is limited to 2 USB, 2 SATA (one for ODD) and 100MB internet.
The keyboard and screen were nice to have when I started out, and the battery came in useful during power outages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would have been a terrible fileserver but it ran PiHole and HomeAssistant in docker with great stability until recently the network interface started having issues.
Fun fact: this was also the machine I used for building Fedora packages for ani-cli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-wont-change-now&quot;&gt;What won’t change now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll go over a few devices I use at home but won’t change now.
They are still relevant as services will interact with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked up a decent-size UPS from the trash a few years ago - it turned out to only need a new battery.
Now it has backup power for my NAS and router.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My networking is done by an ISP-provided all-in-one, which I hate but don’t want to change just now.
There’s also an unmanaged network switch to provide extra wired connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For media, I have a Chromecast (TV is not smart), a Pi 3 with Kodi and a Pi 1 with Volumio.
With the exception of the Chromecast they get their files trough mounted SMB shares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few IoT devices with open firmware I use for home automation and some that aren’t connected to the internet because their firmware is proprietary, outdated and they would be a security risk to my network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;comming-up&quot;&gt;Comming up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Host System - the metal that’ll run my services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Filesystem layout - from disks to directories&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Networking - connecting to the web&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Docker and nextcloud - how not to get in your own way&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Torrent and media management - My Lord, is that legal?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Media serving - the forgotten world of DLNA and UPNP/AV&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Home automation - my home is smart&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Backup strategy - because RAID is not a backup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Migration - moving it all in&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="home server" /><summary type="html">Since August I’ve been upgrading my home server setup. It’s not yet 100% complete, but most of the architectural decisions are already behind me. I wish to document this process so that others can learn from it and as a reminder for myself if I ever forget how I did something. This is part zero of my writeup, which’ll be about the hardware and software used prior to the upgrade. This should serve as a comparison baseline.</summary></entry></feed>